okay we're recording welcome everyone
this is voices with verve a key today my
my friend and guest is layman pascal and
i'm gonna let layman introduce himself
and say why he's here and perhaps you
know initiate the first topic he'd like
to bring into discussion so welcome
layman it's great pleasure to have you
here always a great pleasure to be with
you John
I usually hate introductions mic dancey
is to be like I'm just some guy but at
the same time I'm not a modernist
integral philosopher meditation and yoga
teacher writing and do a lot of thinking
non-dual theology different definitions
of religion and that's probably where
I'd like to start is what's a kind of
new thinking meta level view of what
religion and spirituality are yeah so if
we look at something like just modernism
tends to have this in a way pejorative
notion of what religion is because it
looks back at the traditional or just
the immediately pre-modern definition it
says okay these large popular mythic
membership groups with cosmological
belief dogmas that you actually join
that that's religion and it rightly
tries to distinguish itself from that
right zoom out and you look at modern
pre-modern postmodern archaic and you
line them up next to each other you say
what was religion doing in all of these
paradigms was it functioning well what
can we elicit from all of them and how
do we get them to complement each other
going forward right they get a very
different view and a few that's very
amenable to science I think well you
know that of course I'm an agreement
with you I should mention to viewers
that layman and I have had several
conversations already around these
topics and that's precisely why I
invited him on I've often found what he
had to say I'm extremely insightful and
a provocative of my own thinking so what
would you say like what would you say
what definition if
if that's even the right word I I have
kind of a little bit of a bit continued
in fear of definitions so what would be
the the best characterization I will
allow me a looser term for religion that
is more encompassing of this broader
historical and functional scope that you
put your finger on sure loose definition
and obviously it encompasses a lot of
things it's more like a flotilla
different functions right I would say
very generally that it's the it's the
cultural version of what spiritual
practice is mm-hmm
and that involves bringing together
different genres different functions of
human social experience and trying to
integrate and coordinate them to the
point where a numinous excess is
produced where a gestalt coherence you
know we're getting more than the sum of
the parts out of our social practice and
then that becomes an additional energy
that's capable of sacral izing people
relationships cultural rituals things
like that so I think when it's working
that's what it does and that kind of
organizations and the style that
characterizes different religions
that's an output of that process I see
so let me make sure I've understood you
because I think that's really cool so
you're talking about religion ultimately
in cultural terms that was the adjective
you first invoked and then you talked
about social practices that are
analogous to like what like individuals
do a bunch of things that fall under
this loose umbrella of spiritual
practices things that in which they're
trying to bring about substantial
transformation a forward aspiration come
into a more reliable continuity of
contact with what's they what they'd be
most real what they're ultimately
concerned with that sort of thing and
then there's what you're saying is
there's analogous social practices that
are performing simple similar functions
and when you get in it when they form
I'll use this from like a dynamical
system that gets some emergent excess so
that the system tends to be present to
people rather than just a foreground I
sort of rather than just a background
system of constraints that they're
operating within it sort of presents
self to them phenomenologically they get
us you say I believe you use the
adjective numinous
right they get some sense of an excess
that it's going beyond that it's it's
affording more than it could before it's
taking on a life of its own is that is
that a fair representation of your point
yeah I think that's very fair it's love
you know the social machinery of
apotheosis right function and when it's
performing that function well then it's
really religion izing it's really doing
its job as opposed to it might not be
you might have a group of people who
think they're religious and they're not
performing that function so you got to
use the definition apart and I think
it's absolutely essential
culturally because it's what brings
people together in this numinous excess
it's not just an aesthetic pleasure that
we take in thinking of something as
transcendentally wonderful it's also our
mobilisation energy all right brings us
together mobilizes us which we need in
order to face crises that we have right
and if we don't do that then we kind of
degenerate yeah that's where I would
that's my generalized definition of
nihilism nihilism like not in the
specific idea that you know we've lost
the thought of being by focusing on the
metaphysics of the beings or that I'm
walking around saying I have no beliefs
not that kind of nihilism but a much
more general process of self
neutralization or of the of the nothing
izing of our practices and our values so
that we begin to regress because we lose
the ones that we attain great so yeah so
that that the two points here the one is
that that notion that it's not just an
aesthetic response but actually an
enabling and energizing phenomena that
that reminds me of stones work in
minimal a minimalist account of
transcendence I think he calls at
minimal transcendence where he's trying
to give stone has been consistent about
trying to explain phenomena like
transcendence and completely
naturalistic terms and he points to that
fact he he but he adds it adds an
element to it he's like you he says it's
not just aesthetic but it has to afford
it has to it's almost like an insight
the way it makes it you know Boden's
idea of an insight that it allows you to
do things that you couldn't previously
do so it's energizing and it's also
insightful but I
take your point at a social level but he
also points out it also has a normative
aspect to us it challenges us it
challenges us to kinds of self criticism
and self correction that we otherwise
would not be capable of are you keep are
you happy with outing that sort of
nominate very good I think that's a big
part of what it becomes over time you
know as if this process is occurring and
it moves forward through history then it
begins to gather to itself a variety of
skills and insights and also acts like a
memory of a variety of practices and
skills it moves that forth it wants to
keep itself going so it has to remember
how to do those things right so the
other point I wanted to pick up on is
the you made a distinction between sort
of different conceptions of nihilism and
the one that you were talking about
sounded it sounds very similar or
overlaps to a significant degree with my
notion of the meaning crisis is it is
that a fair interpretation sure I mean
meaning crisis has sort of two aspects
one is there have always been meaning
crises that society wasn't doing its job
getting up to date on the other hand
there's maybe something peculiar about
the current moment yes but maybe
objectively but the meaning crisis to me
why is it a crisis it's because we're
not getting a handle on it
we're not working it properly to get the
results we want and therefore if the
practices that we need in order to
produce the capacitance to give us the
capacity to handle that those practices
are absent right and so the result of
the absence of those practices is what I
would call nihilism in general yeah
regress rather than progress right right
that makes sense so that what then is
best you a similar question in other
contexts and you often gave me really
interesting in what then is the
relationship because now there's sort of
three things in my mind that have come
up in the discussion there's what you're
calling individual spirituality and I
think of that as some kind of overall
enhancement of a capacity for self
transcending and enhancing religio
sense of connectedness that is so
fundamental to meaning in life right and
that's the third so the spirituality
religio and then of course that religio
is connected to what you're calling
religion and we've been you've given me
this so social analog which I really
like by the way this is very cool so of
course these are they both touch on
religio and therefore there has to be an
important way in which individual
spirituality and social religion relate
to each other what's the nature of that
relationship between them when they
bring that up is maybe you want to
criticize this but many people today
self designate in the face of the
meeting crisis as spiritual but not
religious so they try to they see these
almost in the serial or at least
oppositional terms and yet what you seem
to be saying because you've drawn a very
strong analogy and they and they
converge on religio they seem to
actually be deeply interdependent in an
important way so that's that's what I'm
trying to provoke you to yeah yeah so I
mean if I'm thinking of religion as as
something that integrates all these
different kinds of dimensions of social
practice one of those is spirituality
so there's that part of the definition
but at the same time there is this
analogy where people today in in the
meeting crisis have a very they still
have a pretty good sense from their own
internal life that there are practices
that they could do to grow to feel
better to have transcended experience
they're pretty confident in that but
they're not confident that there's a
functioning analog in the society in
which they live they don't see the
coherence the sacredness of the social
system so I would say that the current
society isn't up to speed in that same
way right we don't we need to put there
arguing that there has to be a religion
that incorporates the current situation
and they're looking around and they see
religions that maybe are the residual
incorporation of previous situations but
not something that handles the current
situation right right so part of it is
that you just focus on yourself when you
don't see the social thing working right
now I've argued that that has dangers
associated with it autodidact ism
you know bubble echo-chamber ring and
bubble chambering and things like that
do you think I get the critique I get
the critique that the nuns NO NES are
making that there and you make it you
make it sound interruptive I miss
misrepresenting you that you think
there's actually a needed functional
relationship between the societal
practices and the individual practices
they're looking for them
and and they're not finding them rather
than there saying I don't need them like
there's I'm sorry I know that sounds
like a nuance but there's an important
difference there there's a difference my
things that you're like well what I'm
saying is people who make that claim
about themselves they're making the
critique yeah right
they're saying I looked around and
didn't find it it's not it's not
adequate right and you know part of
that's your own responsibility you
should try to conceive of the religion
that you could get behind not the
religion that you think other idiots are
doing but it isn't largely there right
there isn't the engine of social
coherence to the degree that it's
producing a shared experience of
apotheosis that gives us a sense of the
capacity and meaning we need to face the
situation that we face people are
suffering that lack and so I'm spiritual
I can get extinct experiences I can get
into flow States I know there's meaning
in my life and I know there's practices
that will help I don't see a lot of
success on the social front so I'm
withdrawing I'm skeptical and making
that critique but I think the point of
that critique is that they are looking
to it they're longing for it I think you
know it's need yeah I think the data
bears that out the problem of course
when you have that you know that atomic
spirituality is the meaning that the
meaning that this existential meaning
has virtually no impact on your
communicative meaning or your capacity
could or you or your communal meaning so
these meanings that should be deeply
inter penetrating into reporting become
segregated from each other in kind of a
dysfunctional way uh so here's the
here's the question then that I think
immediately comes to mind well two
questions that one is one of the things
I've said that social systems are not
providing us that would tend to stitch
together
the individual and the social our wisdom
traditions that we don't seem to have
any of those in the West in in any kind
of way that is consonant with other
important normativity z' normative
systems like you know there's a
obviously science that makes epistemic
as epistemic claims on us that cannot be
ignored I'm not offering scientism I'm
saying that you know you you can't
pretend that science isn't important in
your epistemic life you can't pretend
without engaging in self-deception you
have the market of course that you know
and Thomas Bjorkman is made of a really
good case that that's now become our
default deity in some ways it's the it's
the one normativity and then and then
we're seeing right now in the current
crisis the co vid crisis that the
markets useless for this incredibly
complex problem that needs as you're
pointing out it needs a socio-cultural
response not just the social cultural
political response not just a market
response so you've got you've got that
we don't have the wisdom traditions that
have the Qing same kind of normative
status as the market or science for
example or the political arena and then
we also have perhaps exacerbating that
or interacting with that is we're facing
a very pluralistic world now
I mean this is part of what went into
the many different and they shouldn't be
conflated but the many different
postmodern critiques often priests
suppose I'm in a very powerful way a
deep kind of epistemic and sometimes
even ontological pluralism and so the
question is without so what the two
together without you know
well-established wisdom traditions and
without and with within an increasingly
pluralistic world how do we get that
social cohesion that is so central to
religion sorry that was a long question
but it was there's a lot I wanted to put
into it sure it's a long question and
it's a huge topic yeah I think the
answers will come from all different
kinds of directions one of the things
you're talking about is
the relationship between modern systems
and the different kinds of postmodern
intelligences that have arisen over time
one of the things I think obviously
culturally that we're suffering from is
our institutions aren't up to the level
of our insights at the moment yes
modern institutions have given us a lot
of really good things but they can't
handle accumulating dangers and
surprises
right our current kind of democracy in
our current kind of economic market
can't prepare for an asteroid strike yes
have difficulty preparing for pandemic
it's not handling the ecological thing
so there needs to be an upgrade of our
governance and social systems to get on
board with some kind of progressive
insight that that's sort of the bare
minimum we need to do collectively
and I think a lot of people's passion
for progressive politics when they get
into that it is a sign of a kind of a
quasi religious awakening they know
there's something down that road we
could get to if we could get our systems
in line with our best insights now but
the other part of what you said was the
science part and I think religion has
always in folded science and the modern
critique was that pre-modern science is
not adequate and that's an absolutely
appropriate modern critique yeah you
know shamanism Paleolithic shamanism
involved Paleolithic science traditional
religion involved traditional science
yeah there's a reason there was such a
strong solidarity between Aristotle in
the church you know right now that was
the science they could get behind and
they cultivated and protected that
science so at every stage of social and
technological and knowledge
sophistication we have a new thing to
integrate into our definition of
religious cohesion at that level right
right oh if we're not doing that now
then we're not getting religion ization
of the current cultural knowledge
situation that we have mm-hmm so then of
course we're not producing the extra
then we're not internalizing the extra
we're not being mobilised by the extra
it's not happening if we're not in
folding science that's a really good
point now that that that again
I want to throw in the mix that very
often especially your example Aristotle
in the church philosophy has played an
important mediating role between the
science and the religion in getting that
envelop meant to occur and that this
again is where I'm concerned that
because we don't have wisdom traditions
and we don't have people cultivating a
capacity for insight and innovation at
you know a metaphysical or ontological
level that that unfoldment you're
talking about is very very challenging
for us so what I typically see with
response to the scientific worldview
from religious people one is denial and
that's the kind of fundamentalism or
literalism and I think that's a dead end
that's not going to go anywhere uh and
then I think and then I see people
adopting a kind of romanticism while
science deals with the facts and
religion deals with feelings or meaning
and there's some truth to that but
that's not going to get what you want
it's not gonna get that mutual enfold
Minh and then I see you know people
within the theological and philosophical
arena trying to do what you talk about
trying to figure an art do there's some
ways in which my work is trying to do
that how can we get a spirituality that
is consonant and can unfold you know
follow from and unfold that scientific
worldview and and the difficulty I see
with that is there seems to be less a
critique that's often made of my work so
I use my work as an example but I think
it would apply to the other people and
referring to is there's a scalability
issue that these attempts to see that
what Christianity brilliantly did you
know you know between you know a couple
of geniuses
you know Agustin on one end and Aquinas
on the other is they they figured out
how to do that unfold meant but do it in
a way that could plug into you know the
the cultural permutation and / you know
the and and the way the culture
permeates you know lives at all
different scales and and make that work
and so the the challenge and then again
here's where the pluralism you know
makes it difficult right because at
least the church had christened them to
work with
right is how do we get that mutual
unfoldment which I agree with you I mean
obviously I do that my little series is
around it in some ways how do we get
that involvement to work in a way that's
scalable this is you know one of Paul
bender clays ongoing and completely
legitimate criticisms of me how do we
make it scalable especially scalable
within a multi-cultural kind of
situation because we can't rely on
background cultural framework to do the
scaffolding for us yeah how do we make
it scalable and scalable at a tempo
adequate to meet our needs yes yes yeah
well Christianity was scalable but it
took a thousand years yeah yeah yes and
this is Jordan halls point again and
again and again right it's not only that
things are happening more quickly the
rate at which they're happening more
quickly is also speeding up right so
it's got to be whatever it is has to go
fast enough and also be updatable enough
to go faster if it needs to yeah I mean
one of the things we look at our systems
failing we're constantly electing people
who say that they understand the problem
and are going to address it but they're
going to do it in moderate or
incremental forms and that sounds very
reasonable yeah balanced people it
sounds true that's what you want to hear
at the same time if you're gonna
moderately bail out a boat and it's
filling up with water faster than you're
bailing it out then that's not even a
plan yet no no it's a matter of the
tempo being adequate to the moment and
and the scale of the aspiration has to
be the starting point I think oh that's
not even saying that we want to address
it at that scale then we're not gonna
get anywhere right but then the problem
of actually scaling up remains right
there's lots of individual attempts
right and science is full of people who
are spiritual about their science yeah
there's a lot of interpersonal practice
methodologies there's a lot of ideas
about how you refine systems to be more
intelligent and I think that's probably
where you need to go right
smarter voting system you need a smarter
legislature you need a smarter market
you need something whose objective
interpersonal sophistication parallels
the intensity of the shared mutual
experience that we're trying to get
right right oh how do you implement that
he'd have a lot of shared interpersonal
confidence to get a movement going to
make that change
who's leverage would scale the system up
to a degree that would match that
interpersonal experience that was really
good the point you made about you the
way you need this tight connection
correspondence between you said
something like your interpersonal
sophistication right and um the you know
the the overflow that you're seeking
that would give people so the it feels
like a bit of a chicken and egg problem
it feels like people are gonna have the
confidence when they get the sense of
the overflow but they won't get the
sense of overflow until they have the
confidence and that's kind of it feels
like that's the kind of the catch-22
that we're about that's why I've been
trying to do this religion that's not a
religion it's trying to use you I'm
trying to break that catch-22 in an
important way yeah absolutely and I mean
there's a reason why it hasn't happened
yet yeah it's because it has that
structure it's not easy you don't know
where to start
right and when you're starting over here
it's forwarding you here if you start
over there it's thwarting you here yeah
yeah yeah lots of people have to make
attempts to start from a lot of
different angles yes time in order to
see if we can get that momentum going
and religion without a religion is a
terrific project and in a way that's
what religion has always been yeah mine
90% of all religions didn't think of
themselves as religions we call them
that in hindsight yes yes they were
collective spiritualizing attempts to
grapple with the world that they lived
in successfully and more than
successfully so that it paid them back
in a sense of transcendental meaning
yeah so I I suppose this is
self-promotional but it nevertheless
seems independently relevant the project
I'm engaging in with you know Jordan
Hall
and Christopher Massey petrol and Guice
and stock and peter lindbergh
and also we do we've had a discussion
around this the whole deal logos project
about trying to bring back dialectic
precisely because it was a you know a
meta cycle technology that in which
there was an individual spiritual
component of self transcendence that was
wedded with trying to bring about that
interpersonal sophistication right that
would cut which would activate you know
a flow state within collective
intelligence and potentially bootstrap
it up towards collective rationality and
collective wisdom so I see the project
that the dialectic that affords dia
logos logos is when that that that
effervescence you talk about with that
third factor as Chris and I talk about
comes into be in writing you sense it
what you're calling the overflow right
and so what I'm noticing is that you can
take people who don't have the
confidence right that you're talking
about and and Peter are not working
about you know sort of stringing
together a pedagogical program a
sequence of these kinds of practices and
I just had an amazing conversation with
Norah Bateson about her warm data laugh
that I think that's got to be included
in this picture but the idea as a
teacher and a cognitive scientist is how
could we put these together into a
pedagogical sequence a program that
would optimize taking people from bad
faith confrontational you know things
into exactly what you're talking about
that that sense and what I've seen is
people that come in from multiple
different perspectives into these
practices right and in and they don't
even have to come in with good faith
that's that's Edwin Russia's whole point
with the empathy circling but if they at
least hang in there they will get to a
place where the third factor the
overflow happens and then they start to
catch and then what I've been trying to
talk about because I think this was a
point of Socratic dialogue is that
Socrates wasn't just giving us a
competition in in the good sense of the
word of arguments he was also giving a
competition of ways of life he was he
was trying to exemplify and I think this
is what you're pointing to with your
term religion I'm really in liking this
that what I this way of being India
logos is a way of life and the idea is
to
beautiful to make it attractive to
people and this is the way and because
the the catch-22 that we're banging our
heads against this reminds me of the
catch-22 that Plato said about trying to
get people to do philosophy and this is
not irrelevant because we've been
talking about wisdom he said any and you
I I'm asking for charity on the part of
the listeners because I know our current
cultural political context but he used
the seduction metaphor you have to be
seduced into philosophy right you have
to be a track you and this is similar to
what Agnes kahlert says about aspiration
you have to be drawn into it by a kind
of you know perceptual beauty and then
that make that afford you enables you to
see a more moral beauty which then
affords you to see an ontological beauty
and you saw and it's only when you get
to the end you realize why you actually
did the thing you did and so I'm trying
to suggest to you that if we can get
something no that's too strong let me
let me let me let me retreat back from
that was where that was way too strong
my my proposal is one significant way of
trying to bring about the interpersonal
sophistication that you're talking about
well overcoming or at least addressing
the catch-22 by this sort of
beautification that juices and draws
people in right aspirationally is this
this whole project of dialectic and so
and and i know you've read or at least
the chapter that Chris and I have
written and I wonder like is that that
is that something that you see as I'm
not trying to call you into advertising
I want an honest answer from you this is
a discussion like do you see how I'm
trying to situate this and how I know
what I want some sort of reflective
comment on that project and the degree
to which you it might be useful some
pitfalls surrounding it ways in which
you know I don't claim it's exhaustive
so obviously what needs to supplement it
what needs to go around it
sorry that was another big question but
you know this is very slight eek I talk
to catch-22 problem I take the catch-22
problem and the intensification
per interpersonal community and
communication which you put your finger
on I take that to be really central
that's why I'm trying to address it
John's project is laman Pascale endorsed
here's what I would say is I mean I
think that's in some ways the perfect
project for the technological moment
right a lot of this goes back to McLuhan
and the fact that we're transitioning
away from the book culture to the
interaction digital interaction culture
that has to be the premise now rather
than I agree about the book it has to be
an exchange based culture because that's
what we're immersed in so it's very
appropriate to that but it's also I
agree it's a large part of what the wise
the wisdom friends were doing back in
the day right and so there does need to
be this process where faith is the
output not the initial requirements
right you show up to get you show up to
religion to get faithful not because you
already can prove your faith right right
you need to be seduced in right there
has to be a low barrier to entry same as
a video game yeah I people are working
on video games which is I'm gonna give
you a flow State janna groups of another
world but we have to package it we have
to sell it to you we have to make it
easy well yeah the boardroom try to
figure out how to get you in right now
voting could be done that way too if we
really wanted people to vote yeah yeah
so there's a series of practices where
it's got to be really easy upfront and
at the and at some point you are
accumulating faithfulness mmm and down
the line you have to be able to output
that into systems and practices to some
degree right it's got to make that shift
from I'm having personal experience
we're having interpersonal experience
we're having these epiphanies how does
that translate into structures okay to
verify your level of sophistication we
need in our systems now the the the
caution in my mind is to make sure we
don't mistake the interests objective
for the sacral izing per se right right
because yep
because there's an us doesn't mean
there's an i thou mode yet yeah the I
thou mode is a we are actually producing
this extra quality within the US and
that same extra quality can be produced
subjectively or with objects right I can
consecrate my experience of things so
it's not that we're trapped in the I it
relationship and looking at objects and
we have to escape that into the
interpersonal domain all of these
domains need to be studied in such a
ways that they can be brought up to the
level of its production and then the use
of the produced numinous quality right
that's fantastic that's very good point
and this goes towards something that you
and I talked about last time I think
you're alluding to it you know the
concern about when this is really
working as opposed to when people are in
some sense faking it now we have to be
careful about this because you know
people often have to fake it to make it
kind of saying they have to play in
order before they have to do serious
play before they could actually you know
make the transformation so we have to be
very careful about that but like I heard
that that implicit critique in what you
were just saying and you've made it
explicitly to me before maybe you want
to address that too because I know
you've also you've got you know you've
got you've expressed concerns about and
I I agree with them because not only is
there an analogue to sort of individual
spirituality at the collective level
there's an analog to self-deception
right and people there's ways in which
these group dynamics can fall in yeah
you know you have diffusion of
responsibility is a classic example of
how collective systems can really
maladaptive ly make their individual
members perform things like that so we
know about a lot of negative biasing
effects that also exist at the
collective level and and I'm bringing
this up on your behalf because you
actually made this point to me which was
well what what are we gonna like how do
we take care of the shepherding and the
curating and cultivating of the overflow
and and as you said it's got extend out
in
to many of our existential dimensions
not just the interest objective but
totally onboard with that but that just
sort of ramps up the question which is
okay then we got to be really careful
about also sensitizing ourselves to
collective patterns of self deceptive
self-destructive behavior and I know
that was a concern you expressed quite
powerfully to me last time so I wanted
to give you a chance to address that
well whether or not I remember what I
said last time is an open question but
absolutely
upfront fake it till you make it there's
a lot of flexibility and openness in the
foyer of the process on board and you
know the less you require of them
upfront the more you can get them into
that system and to scale up it has to be
really easy for people to get in yes yes
otherwise it'll remain you know an
esoteric Enclave yeah yeah that's that's
a very good point so there's that aspect
but there's also the aspect of not
fooling ourselves with intersubjective
epiphany because they're very real and
they're very important and there's
something people should be working on
doing more of
we should be getting depth skill in that
area right we shouldn't necessarily
mistake inter subjective epiphany for
capacity to enact things as a group ah I
say that's that was a point heart yeah
that's the point
that was the point now I'm glad I posed
my very long I think I've had this
experience maybe you have is there's
lots of really interesting practices
where people can get together and they
can work through their stuff in a way
and they move around they get a
collective hi and I think they
legitimately are sharing a transcendence
together yeah but they don't necessarily
solve a problem they don't necessarily
change it doesn't necessarily become a
new way of living yeah that's what has
to happen for it to affect the outside
world while we know that there are
different ways of organizing groups of
people where you can get results that
are smarter than the individuals in the
group or results that are much worse
than the individuals in the group and
often that's somewhat into
pennant of how they feel a lot of people
have schemes for solving problems that
involve everybody feeling terrible and
dissociated not ideal but it does happen
right so there's there's a difference
between these two and we have to respect
them observe their distinction tease
them apart in order to think about how
they can be better interactive together
you know that was excellent I'm glad I
asked the question because that not
really first of all that's what you said
last time and then you I think you
actually explicate it very concisely and
clearly now this has been one of my
standing critiques and it's been well
received by the way by people like Dai
and there's that a lot of these interest
objective interpersonal communication
practices are all about sort of getting
that enhanced flow the collective flow
state and bringing about all of what you
said but there's no problem there's no
topic there's no problem and this is
what I say that often the follow the
follow Sofia is missing right there
we're not talking about like a technical
problem like you know should we buy more
eggs or something like that well we're
talking about you know the deep problems
like you say about ways of life like
bringing out in a philosophically
problematic form ways of life ways of
being and wrestling with those problems
a lot of these problems it's not
property it's not proper to say you'll
solve them because they're there they're
there issues about the fundamental
nature of human being in the face of the
mystery of of being and so but what we
can get is we can get we can wrestle
with these problems the way we see you
know Socrates and Plato wrestling with
them or the Buddha wrestling with them
or perhaps even Jesus of Nazareth's
wrestling with them because right yeah
it reminds me that the word Israel
actually means to wrestle with God so
that that we as you say we are coming up
with deep responses you know trance
transformations in our ways of being
that we can make deep commitments dude
that's the word I'm looking for
not so much that we get uh you know a
final solution and I use that term
explicitly because I want I want the
dangers associated with that term
remembered now that we get a final
solution to these problem
the you know the deep problems of human
being and ways of being but that we get
a way of life to which we can make a
concerted commitment that will at least
address the particular you know
derivative problems that we're facing
that's what I see in fact as I see that
was present in ancient dialectic that
problematization that philosophical
analysis and by the way Nora is doing
that with her warm data labs right where
she has you know the various groups I
really like the machinery there you have
this you have the small groups and
they're talking about a topic they're
problematizing it in this sense like
health for example is and then people
can move between conversations and
disrupt and transform and so you've got
you basically if you enact a dynamical
small world network that's constantly
restructuring but it's not just about
the interest in your subjective flow
it's about trying to bring about you
know these these existential insights
that allow people to have a more deeper
response to the reality at hand and I
think that is that the kind of thing
you're talking about because I think
there are people out there I'm trying to
address that I see Nora trying to do set
a guy wants to take circling in great
what he calls circling 2.0 in which
right one of my good friends encircling
Taylor he's getting people doing
circling and then they're they're
running experiments where they then drop
a topic into the circle and their circle
you know pursues the topic so there's a
lot of people that I think are really
cognizant of that important critical
point you just made that we've got it
we've got it we've got it we've got a
couple the inter subjective flow - you
know philosophy a-- in some profound an
important way i think that's definitely
yeah i mean once you have like we were
talking about this I mean this process
with this low bar to entry but somewhere
along the way these additional concerns
have to come into play right and there
have to be people there to put that in
our mind and a lot of these people who
are doing these projects and they're all
over there's a lot of people doing good
work and there's been decades
people experimenting with these kinds of
practices and then reflecting on those
experiments and a note saying where
there might be shortcomings and then
trying to tweak circling 2.0 for example
yeah yeah exactly though the more people
who try that and are able to share
conclusions if there's a common set of
principles or conclusions coming out of
that that will be very powerful to start
something going socially yeah I think
you you do need to start in a very
open-ended way up front yep and the
people who are doing this like Nora
she's got a lot of experience already
she's way down that chain yeah very much
so people are gonna come in and you're
gonna do with practices and practices
and move them along to the point where
they start taking responsibility for
solving things and changing their lives
and I do agree that that's largely what
the exemplars of the ancient wisdom
tradition we're doing yeah Socrates's
dialogues don't end in a final solution
to any particular problem but they
demonstrate his way of life he changes
the people around him and it also gives
you a sense of something we're
experiencing that super meaningful that
we can use to validate or critique
systems yeah
when Plato looks at society when they
talk in the Republic they're kind of
bouncing the organization of society off
the achieved personal and interpersonal
successes exactly what goes with that
yes oh that's a beautiful way of putting
it
excellent excellent layman yes bouncing
it off and getting that what goes with
it you know a resonance between the
overflow state and that you know a
particular reconceptualization of a new
way of being and that and you know and
the more specific you know
socio-political consequences that might
have exactly that is beautifully put
well put I'm gonna pause it right here
layman I just need to go do something
I'm sorry I just don't want us to be
interrupted I'll be back in one second
I'll just okay we're recording
again thank you for that little
intervention so um I think that point
you've just made that
sort of that idea you know you get into
the overflow state and then there you're
looking for resonance and rebound and
resounding between and you know about
your you know your speculations in the
good sense of the word where you're
trying to see speculate you're trying to
see a you know in an aspirational sense
an alternative way of being and what
that might look like in terms of socio
political and cultural Reformation and
the Republic is a great example I think
I think that's a really powerful point
that you made so thank you for doing
that yeah that's
I mean involves two things you have to
be up to speed on what the world is like
so you have that to validate and then
you have to be really friendly with you
have to be the filo of Sofia right
you've got to be really familiar with an
appreciative a few good friends with
this yeah experience you can do that
comparison right in a lot of the
traditions whether it's interpersonal or
personal involved contemplatively inand
feeling into and becoming a better
friend to that the benevolent form of
overflow I think that's that's really
well said yeah that's really well said
so yeah getting up to speed to it and we
do that with minds to write like I've I
have I produced by practices or by grace
a trans categorical excess that I find
delightful um then I can think about
that I can test my thoughts against it
that's a system right or then I can test
it against my relationships I can test
it against no we're organizing our
society things like that that's part of
the way in which it does act as a
normative guide on you and Plato talks
about you know that that sense of beauty
doing that for us and scary in her book
talks about how you know the scent the
way Beauty sort of prepares us for
insight and it prepares us for something
outside of our egocentric framework
challenging us and drawing us and and
and like and so it even prepares us for
you know treating things with a just
kind of attention because that's what
the
spirits of beauty rather than just
desire or pleasure like you you get a
sense of you are almost obligated to
give this a certain kind of attention
and it's drawing me beyond myself and
it's making me think about things in
ways I wouldn't have done on my own and
so that's why it tends to act as a
normative touchstone for us the way
you're talking about we can sort of
bounce things off against that if you'll
allow me that dynamic beauty that's
unfolding in the overflow so the
question then becomes I suppose what do
you do with them sorry this question as
it was forming in my mouth was
ridiculously pretentious so I try I want
to answer I want to ask this question
with tremendous respect and the people
that I'm in dialogue especially within
the religious communities know the deep
respect I hold their commitment to their
faith but what do we do still hesitant
what do we do with the existing
religions that's yeah that's a dangerous
question but it's but it's the kind of
question we have to ask and there's a
sense in which it doesn't matter right
which is to say healthy developmental
successful practices individually and
interpersonally are happening where
people think they are in a tradition yes
they are not in a tradition yeah we're
teasing apart success and non success of
practices and you might think you're not
religious you might think you're
religious it's not encoded at the level
of mental self categorization right
right right right and between any two
Christians between a two Muslims
one of them is doing it one of them
isn't same is he too faithless
secularists it's the same thing right so
we need to appreciate I think religion
at a deeper level than our nominal self
categorization and the surface level of
our traditions yes within any set of
cultural constructs and mental
constructs there's depth and success if
you do it but not if you don't right
so I think that's a good question I
think that was a good answer to my
question I think it's I think it's
really good so there's two things that
come to mind one is you know I've been
privileged to have an excellent
discussion recently with Andrew Sweeney
and Zach Stein in response to is his
really good essay on the war in heaven
and I brought up with Zach he Pro he
brought up this notion of convergence
and a different kind of perennialism
he's not talking about the aldous huxley
perennialism he's talking about you know
a potential of a place of convergence
kind of a sacral Commons you know how at
the university they have the Commons
right so the sacral Commons where people
can come in and where convergence is
possible but you're not trying to you're
not trying to enforce conversion you're
trying to enforce convergence so that
you know we can talk and and you know
afford I'm thinking about the way you
know in within cognitive science that
the psychologist isn't trying to convert
the neuroscientist into psychology but
they're what they're trying to do is
afford convergence between and so you
get deep learning you get convergence
and then you get variation through their
disciplines and you get convergence and
variation and I think I'm trying to
propose that as an alternative to we
have to you know you have to we have to
have the same religion right it's more
like no no part of what the religion
that's not a religion is know that
people will belong to many established
religions or none and yet if they're
committed to convergence and not
conversion then we can get what zach is
talking about and I think there's a lot
of people like you said within leads I
know because I get to talk to them
they're amazing people I have good faith
enriched dialogues where you know with
all of Android clay and you know
Jonathan pazzo and Mary Cohen and JP
Marceau you that might might have seen
some of them and though I think those
are all really valuable so I know that
there are people of good faith within
the faith so if you don't tell me that
who are capable I think of what we're
talking about because I see them
enacting it but I do worry and and I
want to try and make it more a little
bit more timely the way in which we are
you know we're getting sort of something
like Dom
side and culture shock within our
culture the way we're getting a
reciprocal narrowing our lives are sort
of collapsing down the way we have this
nebulous ubiquitous thing out there
that's almost demonic and that it might
be striking us and it might not and
we're falling into purity codes lots of
purity code thinking in order to deal
with it and people are starting to
invoke now Zack had a really good take
on this but people are invoking a lot of
religious language to talk about this my
worry is another kind of religion is
going to be potentially one that is
either or both deeply nostalgic in a
fundamentalist way or deeply utopic in a
fundamentals way that there's an aspect
of religion right that won't like your
answer in fact would rather you be an
atheist then give the answer you gave
right I think I'm being very careful
here I've clearly distinguished I am NOT
painting all religious people with this
brush I am NOT saying that I've
indicated specific groups of people
specific people that I think are
opposite to what I'm talking about
so but I think you know that's sort of
if you'll allow me a pejorative use of
this title sort of old testament way you
know that right you know a demonic deity
demanding purity codes and absolute
adherence I think that's a great
temptation right now and I'm using that
word because of its bullet of its
biblical overtones I think there's a
tremendous temptation for that right now
and I see that like those people deeply
almost you know violently opposed to
what you just said to what do you look
what's your response to that challenge
that's an old concern it's happened many
times right yes yeah right the Sufis
have always had to hide out within his
life to some degree in within all the
faith cultures there have been people
who were being more open and progressive
with it and people who were closing down
and it's not just the
Berkeley religious no people who think
their secular can I'd also be moving
into a stress based fall in line purity
code mentality yep yep and maybe we're a
little bit safer because so many people
will be doing it in so many different
ways that they'll get in each other's
way yeah yeah yeah but I'm looking at
all of that under the rubric of my
generalized notion of what Neal ISM is
right right right there these are
regressions and under stress people tend
to regress yes and if there isn't a
functional religiosity at our current
level of sophistication then people will
regress to the last time they saw
something like that yeah
it's very understandable it's it's
unhealthy in the sense that health sort
of stabilizes you where you are and
affords you the opportunity to move
forward yes so these are Neal isms right
they're gonna run into things where they
no longer care about a whole bunch of
things those things count as nothingness
all right and roll back toward a simpler
framework and try to stabilize there and
it's that's absolutely what a species or
an organism or a group of people should
do in a way if they don't have better
affordances roll back to the previous
ones that worked we're gonna lose a lot
of things but we're already losing a lot
of things so it's it's understandable
that that would happen and I think it
almost certainly will happen if there's
no better alternative so we have to try
to create the richness of the religion
that isn't the religion of the
interfaith and trans interfaith sacred
Commons you have a new kind of
religiosity and hope and get these
things going these systems and the way
that systems interact with interpersonal
epiphanies but a lot of that to me is
framed I think like it was for Nietzsche
it's framed around the idea of Health
mmm
the more we know about health the more
we can be on guard right so that people
say to someone who is falling into that
mode ego you know that's not good for
you Jim you're doing a disservice to
yourself and your relationships and we
have these you know we have the doctors
we have the Nutri
we have the therapist we have all these
people throughout our society and their
job in a way should be to keep people
from regressing under the impact of
stresses dealing with traumatized people
all the time we have some tools at our
disposal and if we mobilize them
correctly
that's a buffer against a lot of this
right people come back from the war and
their brains are messed up but we have
physical mental you know neuroelectric
scans we can work on their brain
patterns the more technology and
dispersal of Health protocols we have I
think the more we can buffer that and
the buffering may give us the time to
grow the kind of religiosity that will
provide a progressive alternative to
regressive religion because I need one
way or the other that's really cool
because I've been largely because of
Hans work right I've been largely
critical of the fetishization of health
in our society because it's often served
the heat points out it's served you know
the function of as a God for us and and
it's it has this huge narcissistic
element to it but what I hear you doing
and what really caught my attention is
you're actually you're proposing a
reformulation of what health means and I
like this idea of right that part of
what ill-health means this ease means is
when people regress because of stress
because of scarcity or stress or because
also the opposite there's a lack of
positive affordance so there's there's
famine of affordance and there's also
scarcity right of other things in their
life scarcity of meaning making for
example and the idea that what we should
do is because we've already committed so
much and with good reason but by the way
a to health if we could shift it off the
narcissistic health image you know the
eternal youth that the goal of Health is
the eternal youth that will not suffer
death it will always have as much sex as
they could possibly want if we could you
know if we could shift that the the
paradigm of health off of that to the
individual well let's put it let's
the individual that's aspiring to wisdom
that that's the paradigm of Health and
that way if we could get our
understanding of health we could use the
health machinery and the normativity
attached to help to really move people
into considering meaning in life and
right not regressing in the face of
stress as deeply central to human health
because it's precisely a place to get
back to an earlier point where the
individual project and the social
project touch each other this different
notion of health that you're proposing I
think that's brilliant I think that's
brilliant layman I think it's really
brilliant I have a kind of typical
attitude which is don't don't cede the
battlefield in advance of the battle
right which is to say from my way of
thinking we can put an expansive
positive spin on any concept yeah that
attack the concept as if it represented
only its most regressive and calcified
version right right say you know what do
we want religion to mean what do we want
science to mean I don't just mean 19th
century Newtonian science at the expense
of every other valuable part of life I
mean the science that incorporates
everything we think is important and
true and the religion that does that and
the health that does that and health is
in some ways uniquely situated if we
treat it in a positive expansive way
yeah because it's at the intersection of
of individual and society and ecology
and meaning right it's meaningful
ecologically resonant individual and
cultural value of some kinds when we
when we do it right but that's a that's
a sweet spot that accesses a lot of
things yeah so so tying health more
deeply to what Bishop calls well-being
right yeah
I mean in the Nietzschean senses what
about the great health yeah you have to
have your needs met now in order to get
these overflows yes totally
totally yeah totally I just and the way
you rift on your insight was also
wonderful yeah that that strategy of
reformulations where the mere rejection
and there's a sense of which meta
modernism as a whole
is trying to do that it takes postmodern
is it takes it takes seriously the
postmodern critique of modernity right
but then it it proposes not being
satisfied with rejection but doing what
you just did you exemplify the meta
modernist attitude there no no take the
critique seriously from somebody like
Han for example but in the face of it
reformulate it in a way that becomes
viable for us once again I thought that
was excellent yeah I think that's at the
heart of the meta mater and the intrud
all the yeah
there's a dozen different ways to frame
what this new bigger perspective is yeah
but it's really the critique is
assimilated as the precondition for the
correct definition yes it's not that
it's faulty because we critiqued it the
critique is specifying what the new
version should be the one that meets
those critiques right right right
well said very well said and that of
course just to doing some advertising
again that's that's a dialectical
process that's exactly what a
dialectical process is it's not just
simply oppositional argumentation it is
a process in which you can internalize
critique in a way that transforms it
into a virtual engine that generates
affordances of you know a reformulation
a renewal insight transformation exactly
I think that's exactly the point where
where critique is welcomed as part of
the way in which you bring about the
opponent processing that gives you the
self correction that affords self
transcendence I think I think that's
that's that's a crucial that's a crucial
move you just made there yeah absolutely
and it's you mean that opponent
processing I mean that's the that's the
sharpening of your Zen blade you know
you become properly adapted without
opponent processing yeah totally totally
and then that's interesting because it
strikes me that your insight about
expanding health could potentially be
integrated with with you know things
like the deep continuity hypothesis to
move on with in 4e cognitive science of
seeing deep continuity
in our cognitive states and our
biological States it seems to me that
that expansive notion of health that
you're proposing would be very well
situated within that continuity
hypothesis that our cognitive machinery
and our biological machinery ultimately
share you know important structural
functional organization and operational
principles I think that those who
actually would go together very very
nicely I think yeah this uh you know
when to come back to Nietzsche again
who's bubbling up for me in this
conversation he has a line somewhere
where he says you know if you think you
have reduced the soul to something about
the body
you haven't dispensed with the soul you
just don't really know what the body is
yet yeah yeah the body is capable of
doing that thing you were calling the
soul get rid of the miracle the miracle
is still there you just never think of
it as really intimately entangled you
know if the physiology and ecology and
sociology of what we exist in here yeah
that's what I've been trying to talk
about sort of in terms of the philosophy
of science but that comes out of
cognitive science practice rather than
reductionism you know the soul is
nothing but this chemical process in the
brain you're getting what you just did
which is reciprocal reconstruction both
of the ontology zhh change until you get
a dialectical convergence in which what
you end up with is something radically
other than the two things that you
oppose you don't reduce one to the other
they both go through reciprocal
reconstruction till you get to a place
that's other than the two that you
started
they provide the constraints that enable
you to produce the excess yes exactly
exactly
I I was thinking about this the other
day you know when we think of the sacred
as trans categorical yeah there's
different ways to think about that this
is the total Segway by the way trans
categorical for a lot of people that
means something more primal than any of
the categories right but there's there's
a metaphysical flavor to that it could
mean something
synthetic whereby we're putting things
on multiple categories together in
convergence to produce this I like that
one because it's actionable
yeah or it could mean something that
shifts around yeah right which is to say
you know if you if you laid out on the
floor a big map of all the categories of
the possible types of perspectives and
experience that make up the universe and
there's a mouse under the thing and it
just moves around in different to the
categories yeah no there's at least
three ways which which of these ways do
you think of the trans categorical is
being all right so I think of it mostly
the second with a little bit of a
variation on the second but I think it
falls in up to three you gave me I'm not
trying to be into categorical and my
answer to your question about the trans
categorical I think I see it like the
second but proposal but in this way
first of all I think of the sacred
having to deal with that which you know
I want to make a distinction out between
only horizontal categories but also
categorical differences between levels
of being so I tend to think of the
spiritual and that's going to relate to
the sacral in terms of that which you
know crosses between the categories of
the the cognitive the existential and
ultimately the ontological and it
crosses between them and in crossing
between them it does something like I
talked about the trans world it's not
like you're going to another world
because I don't want the Axial Age stuff
what's the trans world the trans world
is it's like tokens recovery theory a
fantasy so and this is I'm starting to
think more and more of this thing the
idea of this sacred tokens notion of
fantasy was not escapism and not
alternative ism it's not this is an
alternative world or I escaped to that
world the idea is I go there and I
experienced something like culture shock
I have to I have to go to this sort of
significant transformation in my way of
being to be in that world to really be
in that world and then I return to this
world and like at the anthropologist
who's gone to another culture and
returns to their home culture and so she
can now see things in her home culture
that she could never see before right
she can see through the cracks of the
categories that for everybody else seem
like the wall of being right the wall of
their metaphysics but she
says actually there's all these gaps
that you're not seeing and I can see
them she recovers right that and I see
that when people are going trans
categorical they're doing that
Transworld thing they're going out so
that where they can come back and
recover the relation the relationships
between the categories in a dynamic and
transformative way which I think falls
under your synthetic proposal is if I'm
understanding it correctly yeah I think
so the word synthetic isn't quite
glorious enough there's there's a sense
of an activity and a function and a
production yes any use to that
experience if we're able to use it and
that's another big part of this is you
know can you handle the intensity of the
numinous yes right and I think if you're
if you're if you're working it in an
organic way in yourself you know and
self-regulating that process then you
can have a pretty good experience of it
but it can be overwhelming for people if
they're not ready or if they're rigid or
in any other way unhealthy so to speak
yeah and I think that's one of the
things we're facing collectively now
like some people are getting sick some
people are dying some people are going
into fiscal collapse but everybody is
facing traumatic weirdness yes right the
sense that there's something available
in the system now that's just so
peculiar constantly and that we don't
have a place for it and that's one of
the things religion ization has to do is
provide us with the technology to deal
with the trans categorical in a way that
doesn't traumatize us I think that's
excellent so there's I think yeah I
think the notion of the sacred should
always have this opponent-process in
between that which homes us and that
which exposes us has us confront the
numinous always and Kristen and I have
argued that explicitly so I'm in total
agreement with because that's what you
need for that's what you need for
systemic relevance realization your
culture has to be able to move between
the assimilation of home the
assimilation to home and the
accommodation and
or even potential horror of right of
what's outside and only when the culture
can do opponent-process in between that
afforded by something like religion
because I think the sacred traditionally
cross culturally cross contextually has
always been that dynamic opponent
processing between that which homes us
and that which could potentially horrify
us so totally that there's a long
tradition of speaking about the fear of
God yes and it's like we are all born
with that phobia and one of the ways to
correct a phobia is voluntary exposure
therapy yeah it has to be drawn that
area you have to go back and forth you
know we're get familiar with it yeah so
that goes to the second point I wanted
to bring up which goes to the work that
I'm doing with Daniel Greg on the on the
on the cognitive continuum so if this
thesis is right and it's the scientific
thesis so I think it's plausible it's
not established I'm not claiming that
but other people are converging on it
like Newberg and others that there's a
continuum between very low level fluency
of processing insight like when you have
a ha moment flow the work I did with Leo
and area on flow as an insight cascade
mystical experiences awakening
experiences and then you know full blow
and you know you know transformative
experiences
if there is that continuum and what
we're doing is recursively exacting and
complexified through a kind of a
circuitry used to use Anderson's term
Michael Anderson's term the same
machinery I think you could situate
progressive desensitization into the
gradual movement along the cognitive
continuum
teach people the disruptive strategies
that are very low-level that bring about
insight and then teach them the
strategies that are needed to get into
flow and so on and then you can take
people again and so I think there's also
a progressive program for moving along
the cognitive continuum that you could
probably pedagogically sync up with that
progressive program through teaching
people the inter personal things so that
you could get that that exactly what
you're proposing you could get the
progressive desensitization along the
cognitive continuum that is in sync with
people being able to more and more read
move into the overflow I can think of no
reason why that wouldn't work but it's
definitely worth trying well every step
of that process there's a an
encountering more richness in more
detail
yeah there's countering intensities and
trying to assimilate or adapt to those
intensities and there's a bringing
together of making coherence of what
you've got exactly where it operates
sort of as a whole and maybe it was more
than a whole yeah it's very constant in
all those steps although health is also
an important factor in that because
really with people who have bodies right
and their ability to do this thing is
going to depend on you know whether they
have pain in their abdomen whether
they're getting along or whether they're
breathing correctly whether their nails
can allow their heart to expand or not
all these sorts of things totally
totally and and that comes up
practically in like as I said I'm doing
a live meditation class right now not to
try and give people well some of what
we're talking about right now directly
in response to the co big crisis and so
you know and and it's a course in that
it's it's exactly like we just talked
about it's it's progressive it you know
it takes people through this you know
constantly gradually expanding you know
excitation and exposure right um but
along the way right you you have to you
have to pause you have to have question
and answers because people do you have
problems with the body with the breath
with it and it's so it has to be this
you know it has to be very its I you
know it's something that really has to I
want to be careful there I mean I think
you can learn a lot from you know a
meditation book but I think meditation
is like making love but if you won't if
you only reading about it you're really
not capable of it right in an important
way uh and you know and that's the
central metaphor in the tradition I was
brought up in that you know that
meditation is your meditation and
contemplation you're learning to prefer
end yourself the way you would your
friend another person you can't you
can't sort of be friends with somebody
just by you know reading a book you have
to do this this whole other thing so I
take
very seriously what you said because I
see it on a daily basis about you know
trying to finesse in Pascal sense of the
word trying to fit you can't do the
spirit of geometry but you have to have
the spirit of finesse
are you finesse yes you know this
progressive you know expansion
excitation increasing exposure but
increasing you know building of the
person's faith in the sense we're
talking about it here that caught that
sense of continuity of contact about
activity right with you know the the
vicissitudes and the fatalities of human
existence yeah getting that to work very
very carefully
it yeah there there there's there
there's and that's why you know Socrates
was ultimately really worried and Plato
was about writing things down because
capturing that finesse in text is very
hard but we have something different now
we have this right we have this we have
these things that are every every second
what's happening between you and I is
deeply Socratic but we can record it
permanently like we used to do like text
and notice the weirdness because I've
been talking about there's people the
weirdness of the of the medium itself to
bring up on your McLuhan point like look
at how big your faces tomorrow it's like
if we were in our faces filled that our
visual field we'd be really close in
real life right and that'd be like
really socially awkward but the medium
accepts that kind of proximity and
although were present to each other
there's no spatialization so there's no
way in which we're marking status or
role with space right and we're sort of
lit right and and and it's so I think
it's I bet Weinstein picked up on this
but I'm trying to do more with it we're
kind of like you know we're back to what
we used to have when we were in
campfires right whether the brightly lit
faces closely no spatial marking of you
know of status everybody and you know
this this this communal thing and and so
I'm hoping that because we have the
virtual campfires and that because they
symbol on because they join together
things that we thought were previously
oppositional to each other which is the
finesse of dialogue and the permanency
of literature joins them together
symbolically and exacts this primordial
is primordial so CLE because we've been
sitting around campfires across several
species for probably at least you know
800,000 years or so right and Matt
Rossano has talked about how that has
just put the Zap on the evolution of our
cognition and our intersubjectivity so
this weird combination of transcending
you know oral finesse and textual
permanence and yet also harkening back
to the primordial Atif of the campfire i
think the medium therefore holds
something really really precious a
really precious opportunity for us it's
enormous potential if we use it right
yeah you know you either move beyond
literate into non literate or you move
beyond literate into trans literate yeah
it brings the brings back the oral and
archaic and melds it together with the
wins that we got from the cognition of
reading and writing yes and I think it's
a one of a dozen really good arguments
for why shamanism is central to the new
scientific religious awakening right
right the thing I wanted to say was in
addition to all of those practices right
bringing people in and teaching them the
skills and they get a little better and
they little better and down the road
they're introduced to some more of the
problems where they could use their
successes in that whole process is also
always under attack needs to be
protected yes other guys who might
exploit it from individuals exploiting
it themselves
is one of the pieces of religious wisdom
is yeah there are demons they're our
vices there are in tension like
processes that are trying to subvert the
successful process yes we are
intentionally withdrawing collapsing
sabotaging ourselves or you know and
it's debatable whether we say we're
doing it on purpose or whether we say by
viewing it through the lens of doing it
on purpose we gain some leverage over it
could go either way
but there is a you know a demon is your
problem
translated through the lens of
intentionality what's this to happen to
you and the nihilism is like that too
it's not just yeah I I've run out of
meaning its I will there to be a void
yeah yeah you very much yeah
I smash everything outside of me down so
yeah the emptiness inside of me yes very
much
yeah teaching each other to be vigilant
and robust against our sabotage attempts
systematically and personally yeah so
part of the wisdom tradition has to
include that and I mean of course and
that was the and you know the religious
institutions did provide that they
provided protection mechanisms how the
protection mechanisms can be like an
autoimmune disorder they could they you
know I'm thinking of what happens you
know with with the Holy Inquisition and
things like that right
the attempt to protect because Amina
originally you know the attempt to
protect people from heresy was exactly
what you're talking about it's right
well now whether or not all the heretics
or demonic I'm not agree with the
church's history but I'm saying they
were trying to they're trying to create
the functionality you're talking about
they're trying to protect right and
properly protect the health of people as
they're moving through this very
vulnerable transformative process I get
that I do worry about that so let me let
me be clear I think your point is
exactly right that's why you heard me
it's constantly saying yes yes yes
throat so it's very clear that I agree
with it but I'm also aware of verse
Lewis's argument that you know the the
hunt for heresy in the West really laid
the foundation for totalitarian thinking
and totalitarian practices because it's
a kind of it can degenerate into a
purity code kind of thing so doing
teaching people and coming up with ways
of protecting them I think is it's
absolutely necessary I don't I did I
it's it's it's unavoidable but I think
attendant upon that is exactly the
danger that I'm expressing which is
these things these things that are
supposed to be the immune system if you
allow me the analogy protecting the
nascent spirituality and religion can
become autoimmune
orders in a powerful way and so what
what are your thoughts on that problem
that problem of trying to afford the
functionality but what what kind of
things in general you know I'm not
asking you for specific things because
we can't do that yet what are the
principles for dealing with that threat
generally speaking there has to be on
the one hand a really well understood
sociological critique of those processes
yes we all have to study those we all
need to be better at decoding the
ideology and systemic processes that
were embedded in that's a really
important skill going forward now we
need to see those things and sometimes
people are hysterically exaggerated in
in calling out fascism wherever goes
wrong right but that's that's a
dysfunctional or primitive version of
something that's really accurate which
is we have to be on guard against these
regressive collapses in the systems
we're using and you need a meta view in
order to do that right traditional
societies couldn't tell when they went
astray yeah yeah modernity looks back
and maybe dismisses them all as being
astray but it can't tell when it's doing
its job or going astray either so you
knew this interview with something like
a health and development orientation
yeah and and a deep sense of how systems
function especially social systems
otherwise we stand around constantly
looking at the failures of our social
systems and it's not just you know
heresy and people being burned at the
stake it's the constant failure of our
legislature to move us forward and
update us probably yeah totally yeah
yeah a large part of it equally is the
individuals have to have the emotional
and physiological and cognitive capacity
to tolerate strange sensations and we
are this expansion right if they can't
feel that if they can't think well maybe
it's okay to be heretical right that's a
risky emotion in the bodies of people
and you have to be able to relax and
feel into that you have to have a
background of many practices of relaxing
and feeling into uncomfortable things so
that in the moment you can go let's hold
on maybe this needs to be protected
against or maybe I'm just reacting
against the weird feeling here yeah
that's opportunity is something that
comes out of a practice but also comes
out of bodies being healthy enough to
let strange sensations go through them
bodies and minds bodies and minds yeah
and hearts yeah bodies and minds north
so this time in this DuckTales I think
with one of Zack Zack Stein's
central arguments that you know the
religion that's not a religion and the
the the the reconstitution of the wisdom
projects are inevitably bound up with
you know you know as a significant
pedagogical Reformation Reformation
right you know the way we're educating
people we're now educating them under
the sole normativity of the market we
used to educate them also under science
but even that's now being more and more
co-opted but what can this do to make us
better producers and consumers once
again as I get labeled with this
unfairly are not some sort of raving
anti capitalist I'm just I'm I'm
criticizing the market does things yes
it does but to believe that it does all
things and it does things that to
believe that it's omnipotent and
omnipresent and omnipotent as I think
foolish idolatry and so one way is to
follow up and Zack explicitly agreed
with this in person you know that we
should be educating people not just
under the normativity of the market we
should be educating them under the
normativity well like you said of you
know spirituality the religion that's
not a religion wisdom and how to protect
that you know you know often vulnerable
individual or vulnerable group that's
going through some liminal
transformative transition and
transformation yes I think our education
system has to be really broadly
reconfigured and we're actually in we're
right in this we're right we're doing it
right now but we have to the virus has
forced us that's part of his point to
consider I'll turn deeply things that
we're now a radical no you can't get
your key people that well baby maybe you
can right
and so there's uh I think that that what
you just said dovetails very very nicely
with his overall art argument about you
know just a fundamental need to
transform our pedagogical vision like at
a very very deep very deep level and a
very comprehensive level no I agree with
that completely that we I mean a huge
part of all of this is reformulating
what our basic educational principles
are yeah right and that's gonna go
that's gonna run against ways in which
they've been currently adapted to be
exploited by particular versions of
markets
yes exactly well said it's gonna go up
against a whole bunch of people's
anxiety about making any change to those
processes and it's gonna run up against
the problem of we don't necessarily know
what are all the changes we need to make
yeah exactly right and what's the
difference between knowledge and
understanding what does it really mean
to assimilate something now do you get
better how do you grow what what
actually does that and what never
mattered in that process those are deep
questions and that's a big project and
it'd be yeah I think and you know of
course there's also questions that Plato
famously brought into the dialectic
questions about education and he
proposed all kinds of educational
reforms and you know some of them I'm
critical of but the intent and what he
was trying to do was I think meet the
demand that Zack is pointing to well um
I think that's sort of a good place to
wrap it up and I did we go to much
longer nobody will watch this video this
was wonderful this was really wonderful
Leeman I mean I had high expectations
because I know you already but you you
you you went beyond them so this was
really rich and I think very valuable to
a lot of people and I expect you and I
will be doing this again I I'm inviting
you to come back on devices with Revati
again and we'll have another dialogue
week I see that I foresee that you and I
could have an endless series of deep
dynamic dialogues and so I'd like to
invite you back again absolutely I'd
love to do it I like you a lot and like
a lot of people I really appreciate the
effort and the work
putting into all these things the way
you think through stuff the way you
language things people are finding that
very useful these different projects
you're doing I think are making a
difference to people so I appreciate
that I'm happy to be a part of it and I
like you a lot so definitely let's do
another one
okay thank you Thank You layman and I
like you a lot too okay well like I said
thank you very much and we'll talk again
soon